<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands obligations to Captain William Bedlowe the grand discoverer of this most horrid plot.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38414</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3006</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36569</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15730744</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15730744</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104547</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38414)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104547)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1591:107)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands obligations to Captain William Bedlowe the grand discoverer of this most horrid plot.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Th. Dawks ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: borders stained, with slight loss of imprint information.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bedloe, William, 1650-1680 --  Poetry.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678 --  Poetry.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:104547:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 32 -->
            <head>ENGLANDS OBLIGATION To Captain WILLIAM BEDLOWE, the grand Diſcoverer of this moſt Horrid.</head>
            <l>THE World is all on Fire in <hi>Jeſus</hi> Name,</l>
            <l>By quick noſ'd <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> who hunt for Game,</l>
            <l>Whoſe hidden ſubtle Souls in <hi>Malice</hi> burn,</l>
            <l>To ruin mighty <hi>Nations,</hi> and to turn</l>
            <l>Their <hi>Cities</hi> into <hi>Aſhes,</hi> cut the <hi>Strings</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Of all <hi>Societies,</hi> to murder <hi>Kings</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And <hi>Kingdoms</hi> at one blow: O Wicked <hi>Seed!</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Such Monſters <hi>Affrick</hi> never yet did breed;</l>
            <l>The <hi>Tyger</hi> on the <hi>Tyger</hi> will not prey,</l>
            <l>But theſe <hi>Religious</hi> ones have found the way</l>
            <l>To feed on their own <hi>kind,</hi> with a new <hi>Trick</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To rid the World of every <hi>Heretick:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>(For ſo theſe <hi>Mountebanks</hi> do ſtile all thoſe</l>
            <l>Who, hunting counter to their <hi>chace,</hi> Oppoſe</l>
            <l>Their tall <hi>Ambition</hi>) they ſlaughter all</l>
            <l>Who to theſe mighty <hi>Monarchs</hi> will not fall.</l>
            <l>But now, Brave <hi>BEDLOWE!</hi> how had I forgot</l>
            <l>Thy <hi>Name?</hi> a grand <hi>Diſcoverer</hi> of their <hi>PLOT:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>An Inſtrument in Great <hi>JEHOVA'S</hi> Hand,</l>
            <l>To ſave the <hi>King,</hi> and his Beſieged <hi>Land:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Had not this <hi>Providence</hi> dropt on our <hi>Shore,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Magna Britania,</hi> now, had been no more;</l>
            <l>Our <hi>Throats</hi> had all bin cut, we clearly ſee,</l>
            <l>If <hi>Gold</hi> or <hi>Silver</hi> could have tempted thee:</l>
            <l>☞Full Sixty Thouſand <hi>Guinneys</hi> proffer'd were,</l>
            <l>If thou woulds fly from hence, and not appear</l>
            <l>To vindicate a <hi>CA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE</hi> ſo Nobly Good,</l>
            <l>And ſave three <hi>Kingdoms</hi> from a Sea of Blood:</l>
            <l>A Ship, to boot, was proffer'd to thy hand,</l>
            <l>To carry thee to the ſecureſt Land.</l>
            <l>Brave <hi>Godfrey's</hi> pale Ghoſt yet doth cry aloud,</l>
            <l>King <hi>CHARLES</hi> deſign'd for <hi>Slaughter</hi> in the Croud:</l>
            <l>Our Nobleſt <hi>Cities</hi> into <hi>Aſhes</hi> burn'd,</l>
            <l>Three Wealthy <hi>Nations</hi> topſy-turvy turn'd:</l>
            <l>The <hi>Inhabitants</hi> all marching out of doors,</l>
            <l>Planted by <hi>People</hi> worſe than <hi>Turks</hi> or <hi>Moors:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>England</hi> no longer <hi>England,</hi> now, but ah!</l>
            <l>Stil'd by a new Name, <hi>Terra Incognita.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>As once the <hi>Britains,</hi> which we <hi>Welſh-men</hi> call,</l>
            <l>Were by the <hi>Saxons</hi> turned out of all;</l>
            <l>A Lamentable <hi>Story,</hi> which may grieve us,</l>
            <l>When there's no <hi>Wales</hi> nor <hi>Cornwal</hi> to relieve us.</l>
            <l>We had been th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Hunters prey, the Worlds laughter,</l>
            <l>Had not brave <hi>BEDLOWE</hi> ſav'd us from th<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſlaughter:</l>
            <l>Five years thou wert their <hi>Slave</hi> to ſet us free,</l>
            <l>To ſound the <hi>Depth</hi> of all their <hi>Policy;</hi>
            </l>
            <l>They <hi>Mine,</hi> and thou didſt <hi>Counter-Mine</hi> as faſt,</l>
            <l>To blow them and their <hi>Plots</hi> up at one Blaſt.</l>
            <l>Like a Phyſician, that is always ſure,</l>
            <l>Thou didſt not uſe thy <hi>Remedies</hi> for <hi>Cure,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Till the <hi>Diſeaſe</hi> grew ripe, then from thy skonce,</l>
            <l>They and their <hi>Fire-works</hi> were blown up at once:</l>
            <l>A Pill ſo bitter to the <hi>Vulgar</hi> ſight,</l>
            <l>The <hi>Plotters</hi> and their <hi>Plots</hi> were brought to Light,</l>
            <l>Forc'd and compell'd by thy ingenious <hi>Art,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To <hi>Vomit</hi> up the <hi>Poyſon</hi> of their <hi>Heart.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And had not <hi>Providence</hi> thus ſtopp'd the <hi>Flood,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>ENGLAND</hi> had ſwum in her own Scarlet <hi>Blood.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Accurſed <hi>Cain,</hi> why doſt thou wear black,</l>
            <l>Thy Brother <hi>Abels</hi> Garment on thy back?</l>
            <l>We find thee, when that we have meaſur'd right,</l>
            <l>To be a <hi>Judas</hi> not a <hi>Jeſuite.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The <hi>Name</hi> without the <hi>Nature</hi> is a Gull,</l>
            <l>Be like our <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> he was Merciful:</l>
            <l>His <hi>Love</hi> appears how much he did <hi>esteem</hi> us,</l>
            <l>He kill'd none, was killed to <hi>Redeem</hi> us:</l>
            <l>Being impt with Cherubim and Angels Wing,</l>
            <l>Wou'd he have kill'd a <hi>Godfrey</hi> or a <hi>King.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>But there be ſome wou'd have it now forgot,</l>
            <l>There was a <hi>Godfrey</hi> kill'd; nor any <hi>Plot:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>So impudent in <hi>Lies,</hi> with perjur'd Breath,</l>
            <l>They do deny the <hi>Plot</hi> and <hi>Godfreys</hi> Death.</l>
            <l>As thoſe of Old, which we may ſtill remember,</l>
            <l>Wou'd Cancel clean the fifth day of <hi>November.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Into our <hi>Calendar,</hi> let us advance,</l>
            <l>The Murther of brave <hi>Henry</hi> King of <hi>France.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Let <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Savoy</hi> Curſe the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> train,</l>
            <l>Three hundred thouſand were in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſlain.</l>
            <l>All Bonds of ſacred Friendſhip you'l unty,</l>
            <l>Oath of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>You take, untake, neither <hi>God</hi> nor <hi>Man</hi> you fear,</l>
            <l>What you have Sworn, the next hour you'l Unſwear</l>
            <l>Unto the <hi>Teſt,</hi> with double mind you ſtand,</l>
            <l>You have a <hi>Pardon</hi> ready to your hand.</l>
            <l>Theſe are the Men, <hi>brave BEDLOWE!</hi> who unju<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>Wou'd trample down thy <hi>Honour</hi> in the Duſt;</l>
            <l>That by their <hi>Hocus-Pocus</hi> Tricks, in fine,</l>
            <l>Thy <hi>Teſtimony</hi> they may undermine.</l>
            <l>When did the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> teach; pray Read their Sto<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
            </l>
            <l>That killing <hi>Kings</hi> was the next way to <hi>Glory:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>David,</hi> the next Succeſſor was appointed,</l>
            <l>Durſt not lay hands on <hi>Saul,</hi> the Lords Anointed.</l>
            <l>But you, what in the World was never known,</l>
            <l>Have fram'd a New <hi>Goſpel</hi> of your own.</l>
            <l>And being mounted on Ambitions Wings,</l>
            <l>Wou'd fly aloft to Heaven by killing <hi>Kings.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And had not <hi>Bedlow's</hi> hand came to deliver,</l>
            <l>Our Noble Prince had fall'n aſleep for ever.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic_poem">
            <head>AN ANACROSTICK.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>W</hi>hat Bleſſed hand directed thee to pry</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi>nto the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> ſubtle Policy?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>L</hi>et Wiſdom that did ſet thee in the Path,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>L</hi>imit our Foes, and bind their Boundleſs <hi>Wrath.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> wiſh that their <hi>Repentance</hi> truly may,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi>nſwer the <hi>Miſchief</hi> of this fatal day.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>M</hi>ay they that unadviſedly did climb,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>B</hi>e truly ſorrowful for their foul Crime,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi>rect their humble minds to Heavenly things,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>D</hi>aſh all their future hopes of killing <hi>Kings:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>L</hi>end them a melting Heart fill'd full of Terror,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi>pen their eyes that they may ſee their Error</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>W</hi>iſdom that tames the raging of the Seas,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi>nd all our Difference in Love and Peace.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Th. Dawks,</hi> His Majeſties <hi>Briti<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Blew Anchor <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Weſt-End of <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
